[Music]
e for
I have mentioned in our podcast in many
episodes that one of the important
aspects of CERN is anchoring the talent
in Europe and you are a great example of
this like someone who started in CERN
and then basically started not one but
many important companies and now Europe
as a whole is basically benefiting from
the fact that well CERN was there to
start your career so can you describe
your story so far yes I came to work at
s in the year 90 when I was still a
student and I was doing my master
thesis H and um actually I started to
work on the big science I was fascinated
by it but in
93 our director General Car Rubio is a
no Lage he announced the idea to build a
um new reactors uh that were safer and
safety was a concern at the time for
nuclear
after uh the accident of chobia so I was
fascinated by this
application uh actually at that time C
was really a place for for the big
Sciences so no space for
applications H and that was like one of
the very few examples of where the
science would have contributed to
Something in the real world uh one uh
example was positive emission tomography
and application of
detectors uh
into um into the real life of uh of
people this one could have been uh
fantastic so I started to work with him
we discovered that uh possibility to
make a safe R could be the use of lead
as a
coolant that was already used in the
military application of nuclear summon
by Russians and uh we had the chance
because s is an international laboratory
to uh to exchange with the Russians and
to transfer the technology toward the uh
community of uh researchers in Europe
and that is what happened uh so for many
years we developed the this design and
we Advanced the science but that was not
a good time to uh to transfer this
technology into a company but uh one of
the patterns that we develop for lead
had an application nucle medicine mhm so
I
asked uh the license to sell of this
pent and uh that was
2001 and uh actually uh at that time
there wasn't any technology transfer
offic system uh it's uh it's fun but um
uh the big science in the past was not
having a lot of attention into uh
technology transfer and patenting and uh
and uh startups and so on uh so uh the
uh I was actually I had the first
license from s uh from the newly uh
formed technology transfer office so I
was kind of considered the first startup
of s but this startup had a lot of
success because in 15 years became the
biggest company nuclear medine uh in the
world and uh uh we listed the company on
NASDAQ in Us in
2015 and from the from the market
Novartis made an offer of 4 billion for
the company uh so we that was possibly
the uh the biggest um um biotech sale of
a French company because the the company
was strange uh ever done so far so very
big result uh so now uh we I'm trying to
do the same innovation in nuclear energy
so coming back to what I wanted to
develop in the 90s Kia finally we think
it's the time to do so
what gave you the courage because you
were trained a physicist and then you
tackled engineering issues and business
issues and so on because atress you can
just ask yourself well if this problem
can be solved some engineer would have
done so already so what give you the
courage in the first uh
time uh I wanted to have uh I I
considered that uh it was not the very
difficult time for politicians to to
invest into Nuclear So I could I I I
could have done it only with private
money uh but nuclear energy with private
money at the end of the 90s or beginning
of the 200 to 2000 was very difficult so
I thought it was a good step to go
through nuclear medicine and I wanted to
prove myself that I could be a good
manager in order to put the energy
application
later um and uh uh so I think it's the
same courage that every entrepreneur
feels when he wants to do something new
um and uh it paid off uh now uh is a I
have a lot of experience so I need a
little bit less courage but the the
challenge is uh supposed to be much
bigger so now I'm I'm using a little bit
of uh um the lack and uh and the uh
bravery that you have when you're young
and I use a little bit more experience
and uh and know how uh entrepreneurial
know how to achieve even a larger
objective that is making such a big
innovation in the field of energy so in
economy we usually have the like the
economy of scale you want to make
everything as big as possible in
technology we try to make the things as
small as
possible and the nuclear reactors are
Technologies which are supposed to make
money so how are those two basically
different directions
balanced yes we uh at the beginning the
nuclear technology was u a state public
technology no financed by by the
governments uh and uh so the invested
money was less relevant that for today
where we want to develop nuclear for uh
fuel by private
money um and I think the nuclear uh got
uh very success even if it's not visible
because in a country like France where
uh there are a lot of nuclear
installation there has been investment
by the government but at the end the
electricity is very cheap uh same in
Finland just uh Finland just open up a
new reactor and the electricity build
for finish people dropped
75% so that's uh that's uh interesting
because even even if nucle is perceived
as being very expensive still is
translating into uh cheapest bills for
the
population uh so that's an interesting
aspect what we are trying to do is uh is
to make a uh a good investment and uh
and cheaper for the population which is
a little bit of a challenge but um uh to
do this we have to go smaller in scale
MH so uh we nuclear was searching for
economies of scale by building bigger
and bigger now we have to choose the
size that makes economical sense for an
investment and that size is such as the
building is very fast uh we need to
build nuclear rectors in 3 years no more
so that the investment period is small
uh we need to make the size of the
investment reasonable uh because we can
leverage of a lot of private money if if
the amount of money engaged is is less
so we are open at kind of a new economy
for nuclear we as the small M elector
Industries not only us of course and
this a nice challenge I think this is
the right time to to have this challenge
because we need a decarbonized energy
and we need in Europe en Independence so
these two new strong driver can
um with a different economical approach
can really make nuclear successful also
from the economical point of view I
think most of our listeners haven't seen
a reactor ever so what is small for you
just like a room size is a smaller
reactor or well it's the biggest we can
do with
uh we have components that we can easily
manufacture and transport so that that
is the is more so something that can fit
into container that can be shipped
somewhere or this is too small because
uh Nu reor still uh produce radiation
while it's used activation and so on so
you we have a we think the smallest uh
that makes sense economically for us is
certainly for electricity production is
around 200
megab um because the larger components
become a cylinder of 6 M of diameters
and 6 m in ey so it remains very small
then you you need components inside you
need components outside like even the
turbine it's it's almost the same size
so um so that that is the side you can
go smaller for specific application if
you go to naal application you need to
go smaller um space application because
you can build a nuclear engine the space
as well so really you need to go small
and comat so there there is an
application a size for every application
certainly the the 100 megabat
application can produce electricity but
can produce at the same time heat for
the for the industry and this is one of
the very important kind of application
that we can uh leverage on as a small
director Community the one observing the
uh energy um uh the the industry that is
using a lot of energy for like the steel
industry uh and and chemical industry
and so on uh they needs to decarbonize
and it's currently using gas essentially
as a mean to produce energy
cheaper when I told my friend that I'm
going to this event he asked me what is
new about this because we have
submarines with small reactors we have
ships so is it just they can afford to
be well inefficient and costly and you
now are just trying to make something
that is wor building or is it a
different I I think that the defense
industry that is the one that fuel this
more model
vectors uh was not was a bit careless
about uh civil application in cost at
the certain moment so they were
searching for different optimization
clearly our our application goes in the
direction of absolute safety uh that for
us means passive safety so uh reactors
that cannot have any accident that is
destroying the
machine uh that is uh but only uh
problems that can be solved uh with
trans and that don't create the the
nuclear accident of the past and then of
course the cost and and uh the
optimization of the investment so we
have different drivers that's why we are
adapting this kind of uh designs to the
Civil industry and uh in this adaptation
if you
deploy uh a new technology like us you
have the possibility to make things like
very cheap very safe and very
interesting from an investment point of
view this is our
challenge no there is an argument and
I'm not comp completely agreeing with it
but just want to well hear a perspective
aren we trying to be too careful about
nuclear energy
like way more people are dying by well
the pollutants from burning coal and so
on so maybe we can accelerate it the
transfer to nuclear energy it would be
actually saving lives even if the safety
isn't there or isn't as high as it is
right now yeah the nuclear energy so far
has been the safest form of production
of energy uh so it is already safe what
we have to take care of is the
perception of the public because the
perception of the public is opposite is
uh it's a bit
surprising uh but is not considered safe
uh nuclear waste is considered a problem
uh but nobody ever ever was contaminated
by nuclear waste and there was never
been an accident due to the nuclear
waste so and the nuclear waste is
contained so it's is is incredible
because you don't contain the ashes from
the burning of coal that are producing
millions of
death so it's it's strange how the
perception of the population can really
change the narrative on on the
technology so I think we have to solve
this we have to solve this perception of
the people towards the technology which
is a general problem it's not only for
nuclear and how can you do it because
well nothing happened today at the
nuclear uh well uh nuclear power plant
isn't a very good headline for news so
we are interested when something big
happens there is accident something that
spreads around the world but every day
where no plane
crashes no accident at Power Plant this
is a very bad headline so how can you
basically change the how people feel
about nuclear energy I think the
youngest generation are helping us a
little bit because uh uh the the nuclear
fear has been brought for many reason uh
first nuclear has to to scare the
population because of the destructive
energy of a bomb but also for something
that does not essentially exist which is
the uh nuclear uh contamination from the
explosion of a bomb uh that we saw
destroying the world in the uh movies of
the 60 the 70s and the
80s uh then we had uh to uh defend
ourself from the uh oil industry that
was putting shame on nuclear and and
enlarging the fears of the population
because they were fearing competition
from nuclear and they so they destroyed
the and uh the the delusion of
the world of that time that nuclear
energy could bring benefit to humanity
and they managed to leverage on the fear
on nuclear also to to you know to
benefit for their industry so but the
Young Generation they don't have the
history of chob
accident uh they don't they have less of
a history of fukusima and they find out
that accident like Fukushima didn't
cause any that people for the nuclear
accident did cause um uh a contamination
that is uh creating a problem with the
environment uh so by discovering this
they feel little bit uh uh um strange
because uh they said so why we don't use
nuclear energy since it's a form of
decarbonized energy that conceived the
problem from the planet from another
problem which is the climate change uh
so they can contribute but we have to
also make an effort in informing the
general public the the generation like
Min that still biased by the The
Narrative of the past the movies is
incredible but the movies made made a
lot of uh damage um there was an
accident in 78 in uh U us uh that didn't
cause any debt and didn't cause any
contamination nuclear action with no
effect on nothing uh but two weeks
before there was a movie catastrophic
movie that described the same accident
and the result of um of this movie uh of
the accident occuring just uh after this
movie was that uh uh in the in the next
50 years 5
z uh us built only one reor they built
100 before or the the accident one after
that is crazy for a movie The Korean
industry stopped uh to develop nuclear
rectors uh after a movie Pandora that
described another catastrophic accident
with nuclear it's crazy the movie
industry has created a lot of damage
because they like the journalist they
like the the bad news the catastrophic
news and uh things to describe that
destroy the world and so on so nucle has
been easy to do this because nuc unfort
started the um in the history of
humanity with a bomb so not a good
start and well I think Three Mile Island
accident might have negative death toll
because some people discovered they had
cancer because they screened after the
accident but the tumor started growing
before before it so they just went to
the doctor and their lives have been
saved by
this little
CH the unfortunately when you what
happened for example in chob was that
there were discovered more thyroid
cancer that is caused by one element
that is released during a a severe
accident that is IOD in
131 um but often in on col ology if you
do more diagnostic you find more tumors
but in the end the number of dead people
for this kind of tumor was exactly the
same and I'm talking about 35 years of
clinical studies
around um uh thyroid cancers in the
popul in the European population and
specifically in the population close to
uh to
um the ch
reactors on
belus Russia and and Ukraine so um so
the evidence uh of of the medicine
showed that that there was no uh no no
consequences only a few like three three
or 4 thousand people are suspect could
be could be uh could there could be a
slight increase but essentially is in
the
statistical fluctuation so still is not
an Evidence of of any effect on the
population this if you tell somebody who
not read all of the relevant uh uh
bibliography on this clinical study they
will laugh and say come on there are the
uh uh you know the chob accident created
so many theform the
children this is in the mind of the
people uh definitely know the form sheet
that not even Al one it's uh so it's a
little bit difficult to um you know to
go against uh the things that have
sedimented in the imagination of the
people for so many years yes yes yes and
well you at nuclear are working at small
modular
reactors how do we see the future we
will use a mixture of small reactors and
big ones or some count will prefer the
big ones and maybe small island
countries will opt for smaller reactors
or some factories will have reactors on
their own to generate heat maybe not
even
electricity certainly I am 100% sure
that there will be mix of technology and
of course not only reactors also
Renewables other kind of
Technologies uh possibly the market will
make the difference so uh successful
cheap rea can maybe be more Swift spread
in the future than
others uh there is an advantage uh if
you you know invested in technology and
if you have a big reactor there is an
advantage for a country still to build a
big this big
reactors uh because they lower the price
it's a huge investment for the country
but at the end they lower the price of
the bills for the
people um and uh they create a lot of
jobs as well so is
and there are some good sides also in
having a large and costly projects but
the mix is the right uh is always the
right uh choice and mix that is adapted
to the
need of the countries there would not be
built solar cells in in the
northern you know uh countries of Europe
does not make any sense uh I would uh
unfortunately Italy has uh very little
wind mhm so windmills for us are very
expensive we have some in the south of
Italy in the Seas but uh it it's not
extremely efficient and uh you cannot
serve M the northern Market where there
is essentially no wind MH um which is
the the market today that needs more
electricity so you always have to adapt
and of course the industrial use is a
massive uh user
of uh of this um potential use of of
this new technology so we we we we need
to to to be adapted and to build a mix
of Technologies so last two questions
the first one is during starmus I had an
interview with Steven Trum also Noel
Prize in physics but expert in energy
and his claim was at the end of the
century we can hope for a mixture of
Renewables and nuclear but the end of
the Millennium maybe also nuclear fusion
so do you keep an eye on this technology
as well or is it too farfetched and in
the future for now I keep an eye I'm
even in the board of a nuclear fusion
company in
Germany um at the moment uh I feel very
complicated to build an economical
Fusion
reactor uh because even if many
technology Gap will be filled in the
future still is a complicated technology
so I see how simple is the nuclear
reactor today is a you know heating
tubes and and the steam generator and
the turbines it's basically steam engine
so yeah uh so it's very difficult for me
to imagine um a competitive uh nuclear
fusion system but maybe uh you know we
need absolutely to develop this kind of
system because you know when you develop
a technology you might have
surprises uh so I I I really hope that
one day also Fusion will play no role in
the in the mix uh of of in the Energy
Mix because I'm sure there might be uh
suitable application for Fusion uh as
well I said last two questions but you
reminded me a thing I wanted to ask is
the progress driven now purely uh by
Engineers or do you hope to see
something new from physicist like new
mechanism happening in the nuclear that
can well enhance
something people Academia how can they
help uh maybe even theoretical
physicists I am exposed very much
technology and uh and as a physicist I
must admit that the last uh uh steps is
always done by engineers and uh and uh
so it's uh uh
is is difficult to predict because uh
well we have brought innovation in
fields that we couldn't imagine before
starting our activities as physicist so
uh I'm pretty sure that will happens
again but uh saying when and with what
is very is very difficult certainly
nuclear physics and fishion Etc is very
simple very well known technology and
still we have a lot of application
possible like the nuclear
batteries uh using the the energy of uh
active material uh from the nuclear
waste for example it's
uh is still engineering problems not
really physical problems
so it's good that the big science is
still very active because we we need a
to have a new ideas for the future so
hopefully the perception is changing and
we are moving from the we Are Not Afraid
towards the we are enthusiastic about
the future and the changes that are
coming and the changes have to be
brought by students current students so
what would you recommend them what would
be your message to our young listeners
to the young listeners uh I uh I would
really recommend to go into the stem uh
because uh all the Innovation is massive
in the industry and we have a massive
need of
Engineers
scientist uh technologist and so on so
uh if you want to work in the future for
sure uh choose a stem if you don't want
to work don't choose stem because you
you will you will do it all the time you
will be very much requested from the
market but that's encouraging there's a
lot of work to be done and but it's
worth doing yes and also I I really hope
that more ladies will be encouraged to
to go into the stem because there is uh
still uh a traditional lack of uh woman
in in this field and you know I really
hope that uh ladies become enthusiastic
about a scientific um uh world and uh
the work into scientific field
okay so hopefully in 10 years you'll be
able to employ them at new Cleo yeah we
have unfortunately only 27% at the
moment uh will be a dream to reach 50
soon
50% so thank you for answers and
hopefully see you next time in Slovakia
thank you very much thank
you for
[Music]
might for